Guide to the Charles McKinley Papers 1930-1968
Special Collections and University Archives, University of Oregon Libraries
Charles McKinley papers
1930-1968
Ax 627
Special Collections and University Archives, University of Oregon Libraries 1299 University of Oregon Eugene, Oregon, 97403-1299 (541) 346-3068 spcarref@uoregon.edu
28.5 linear feet 19 containers
Charles McKinley was a professor of political science at Reed College in Portland, Oregon from 1918 to 1960. He was particularly interested in the theory and practice of public administration and planning. As a specialist in these fields, he often served on government committees and commissions and he also wrote studies on the impact of the Federal government in the Pacific Northwest. The collection consists of files accumulated for specific projects undertaken for government or private agencies, or for personal research. Included are correspondence, minutes, reports, memoranda, position papers, interviews, and documents relating to such groups as the Bonneville Power Administration; California Department of Water Resources; Department of Agriculture Administrative Council; National Planning Board; and the Oregon State Board of Forestry.
19 containers
McKinley, Charles
Box 1-19
Biographical/Historical note
Charles McKinley was born in Fulton, South Dakota and educated at the University of Washington and the University of Wisconsin. From 1918 to 1960 he was professor of political science at Reed College in Portland, Oregon. He was particularly interested in the theory and practice of public administration and planning, and as a specialist in these fields often served on government committees and commissions. He wrote two major studies on the impact of the federal government in the Pacific Northwest: Uncle Sam in the Pacific Northwest (Berkeley, CA, 1952), and The Management of Land and Related Water Resources in Oregon (Washington, D. C., 1965).
The papers, arranged as record groups, are the files accumulated for specific projects undertaken for government or private agencies, or for personal research, and include correspondence, minutes, reports, memoranda, position papers, interviews, and documents. Major files are: Bonneville Power Administration; Bonneville Regional Advisory Council; Bureau of Land Management; California Department of Water Resources; Department of Agriculture Administrative Council; Northwest Regional Council; Forest Service; National Planning Board (National Resources Board, National Resources Committee, National Resources Planning Board); Northwest Forest Pest Action Committee; Oregon Legislative Interim Commission on Administrative Reorganization, 1930; Oregon State Board of Forestry; Oregon and California Advisory Board; Pacific Northwest Field Committee (U. S. Department of the Interior); Pacific Northwest Regional Social Science Research Council, study of administration in the Department of Agriculture.
Collection is organized into the following series: Bonneville Power Administration; Bonneville Regional Advisory Council; Bureau of Land Management; California Department of Water Resources; Department of Agriculture. Administrative Council; Electric Power File; Ford Foundation; Forest Service; National Planning Board; National Resources Committee; National Resources Committee. Alaska Resources Committee; National Resources Committee and Pacific Northwest Regional Planning Commission; National Resources Committee. Region 10. North Pacific Planning Project; National Resources Planning Board. Region 6; Northwest Forest Pest Action Committee; Oregon. Legislative Interim Commission on Administrative Reorganization; Oregon. Legislative Interim Committee on State Government Administration; Oregon. State Board of Forestry; Oregon and California Advisory Board; Pacific Northwest Field Committee; Pacific Northwest Regional Planning Commission; President’s Committee on Administrative Management; President’s Water Resources Policy Commission; Princeton University; Social Science Research Council; Valley Authorities; War Production Board; Personal Papers.
Collection is open to the public.
Collection must be used in Special Collections University Archives Reading Room.
Gift of Mrs. Charles McKinley in 1971.
McKinley, Charles--Archives
Reed College (Portland, Or.)--Faculty; United States. Bonneville Power Administration; United States. Bureau of Land Management; United States. Dept. of Agriculture
Natural resources--Northwest, Pacific; Political science teachers--Oregon--Portland; Regional planning--Northwest, Pacific; Water-supply--Oregon
City Planning; Colleges and Universities; Forestry and Forestry Products; Government and Politics; Oregon; Pacific Northwest History; Portland
- Inventory (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Bonneville Power Administration, 1939-1954; 3.0 linear feet (Box 1-2)
  Correspondence, memoranda, documents, and notes on all aspects of the Bonneville Power Administration, including administrative management, personnel, legislation, accounting, rates, sales, relationships with private utilities, industry, the Corps of Engineers, the Bureau of Reclamation, and the National Reclamation Association. 1939-1949.
  There is also a ten-inch file of carded notes and interviews on the Bonneville Administration, 1944-1954.
  These files and notes and interviews were used by Mr. McKinley in his monographs, Uncle Sam in the Pacific Northwest (Berkeley, 1952), and The Management of Land and Related Water Resources in Oregon (Washington, D. C., 1965).
- Bonneville Regional Advisory Council, 1944-1968; 1.0 linear feet (Box 3)
  Minutes, 1st-19th, 22nd, 1944-1952. Unnumbered, 1961-1968. Also, memoranda, and correspondence concerning the Council and its activities and positions, 1944-1953, 1961-1968.
  The Bonneville Regional Advisory Council began March 31, 1944 as a “Conference on Bonneville Power Administration Program and Policy,” convened by Paul Raver, administrator. At the third such conference, October 9, 1944, the group selected its name, and elected officers and appointed committees. Mr. McKinley was a member of the Conference and Council from its inception.
- Bureau of Land Management, 1952-1964; 4.0 linear feet (Box 3-5)
  Data on the Bureau of Land Management in the Pacific Northwest, particularly its conservation and recreation activities, 1952-1964. Includes letters, interviews, reports and documents.
  With these files and notes and interviews were used by Mr. McKinley in his monograph, The Management of Land and Related Water Resources in Oregon (Washington, D. C., 1965), chapter 11-14.
- California. Department of Water Resources. Board of Consultants for Assembly Concurrent Resolution no. 14, 1958-1959; 1.5 linear feet (Box 5)
  Working papers, 1958-1959. Includes administrative correspondence, minutes of meetings, intra-committee memoranda, drafts of reports, and documents used as references. One folder contains a set of studies on the California Water Plan and related subjects by Mason Gaffney.
  California Assembly Concurrent Resolution no. 14, April 17, 1958, referred to the Department of Water Resources Bulletin no. 3, “The California Water Plan,” (May 1957), and ordered that an investigation be made of the impact on the economic and social structure of the state of various water policies, their financing, pricing, and repayment.
- Department of Agriculture. Administrative Council, 1940-1942; 1.5 linear feet (Box 6-7)
  Records of the executive secretary, 1940-1942. Includes many interviews, memoranda, and internal documents, among them Stanley P. Williams, “Investigative activities in the Department of Agriculture,” (n.d.); E. H. Clapp, “Historical development of decentralized administration in the Forest Service,” (n.d.). McKinley, “Report of the Committee on small claims,” (n.d.).
  In September 1940 the Department of Agriculture employed Mr. McKinley as “Head Administrative Officer” in capacity of executive secretary of the USDA Administrative Council (established February 12, 1940 by Department Memorandum 842). He planned or conducted studies of the management policies of the Department of Agriculture, particularly department action programs at the county level; and the integration of the department’s programs in the Southeast region.
- Electric Power File, 1946-1960; 1.0 linear feet (Box 7-8)
  Correspondence, documents and related material on hydroelectric power generation and distribution, and Federal power policy, 1946-1960. Includes files on the inter-tie issue, Pelton dam decision, partnership proposals, the Hell’s Canyon issue, and the Governors’ Power Policy Committee.
  Related material is in the Bonneville Power Administration file.
  These files were used as source material by Mr. McKinley in the writing of his two major monographs referred to above, and in his reports, lectures and papers.
- Ford Foundation, 1952; 1.0 folder (Box 8)
  Study of the history of the Northwest Regional Council, 1952. Correspondence and report.
  In July 1952 the Ford Foundation asked Mr. McKinley to “examine the work and results” of the Northwest Regional Council (1938-1943), to aid the Foundation in determining whether the Council or a similar organization should be reconstituted.
- Forest Service, 1949; 1.0 linear feet (Box 8)
  Study of certain filed activities of the Forest Service, and their relation to headquarters policy, 1949. Includes interviews, statements by Forest Service personnel, and by citizens, and a draft of the study, September 19, 1949.
  In June 1949 E. W. Loveridge, assistant chief, Forest Service, asked Mr. McKinley to make a study and review of certain Forest Service policies and activities in Oregon, Colorado and Utah, particularly as related to the policy of administrative decentralization. The request was made in response to critical remarks in House Report 384, 81st Congress, 1st Session, in connection with the Department of Agriculture appropriation bill.
- National Planning Board. (National Resources Board; National Resources Committee; National Resources Planning Board), 1933-1936; 1.5 linear feet (Box 9)
  The National Planning Board (under the Federal Emergency Administration of Public Works) was established July 30, 1933 to advise on comprehensive program of public works through the development of regional plans, surveys and research. It was abolished by Executive Order 6777, June 30, 1934, which established the National Resources Board, to prepare and present to the President a program for development and use of land, water and other national resources. It was abolished by Executive Order 7065, June 7, 1935, which established the National Resources Committee, which assumed the duties of the National Resources Board. In turn, it was abolished, and its functions transferred to the National Resources Planning Board, established in the Executive Office by Reorganization Plan no. 1, effective July 1, 1939.
  The files include:
  National Planning Board. Minutes, 1st-17th, September 7/8, 1933 – June 29, 1934
  National Resources Board. Minutes, 1st-7th, July 1, 1934 – June 13, 1935
  National Resources Board. Advisory Committee. Minutes, 1st-19th, July 11, 1934 – June 15, 1935
  National Resources Board. Industrial Committee. Minutes, 1st-9th, August 28, 1934 – January 16, 1936
  National Resources Board. Land Planning Committee. Minutes, 1st-26th. November 7, 1933 – November 11, 1935
  National Resources Board. Mineral Policy Committee. Minutes, 1st-3rd. Mary 23, 1934 – February 27, 1935
  National Resources Board. Recreation Committee. Minutes, 1st-3rd. December 19, 1935 – February 25, 1936
  National Resources Board. Science Committee. Minutes of joint meetings with advisory committee. 1st-2nd. March 25, November 12, 1935
  National Resources Board. Technology Committee. Memoranda. January – March 1936
  National Resources Committee. Minutes, 1st-5th. June 13, 1935 – April 21, 1936
  National Resources Committee. Advisory Committee. Minutes. 20th-38th. June 30, 1935 – September 12/13, 1936. (These minutes continue the numbering of the National Resources Board Advisory Committee.)
  National Resources Committee. Water Resources Committee. Minutes, 1st-11th. July 24, 1935 – July 26, 1936
  National Resources Committee. Subcommittee on Flood Control and Water Storage Projects. Minutes, 1st-2nd. July 1, 9, 1935, and Report of Conference, July 21, 1936
  There is also a file of letters, memoranda and other papers relating to the work of these agencies, 1933-1936.
  With these minutes and documents is a five-inch file of carded notes and interviews, 1935, on planning, planning agencies, and related matters.
- National Resources Committee, 1939; 0.5 linear feet (Box 9)
  North Dakota study, 1939. Miscellaneous correspondence, and report, 1939, and interview files.
  On July 20, 1939 the North Dakota Advisory Board held its first meeting. It had been established by the Governor in lieu of the North Dakota State Planning Board, which the legislature had not budgeted. At this meeting the representative of the National Resources Committee offered the assistance of the Committee toward making economic and social studies of North Dakota. The result was Mr. McKinley’s “Planning for the Rehabilitation of North Dakota,” (n. d., August 18, 1939. Mimeo.)
- National Resources Committee. Alaska Resources Committee, 1937-1939; 11.0 folders (Box 10)
  Working papers, draft report, and miscellaneous correspondence, 1937-1939.
  Concurrent resolution no. 24, August 21, 1937, U. S. Congress, requested a “comprehensive plan for the development of the resources of the Territory of Alaska.” In a letter of August 30, the President directed Harold Ickes, chairman of the National Resources Committee, to have such a study made. An Alaska Resources Committee was formed to respond to the President’s directive. It was headed by Carl L. Alsberg. Mr. McKinley was a member. The staff of the Pacific Northwest Regional Planning Commission cooperated. The report of the Committee was published as Part VII of Regional Planning, by the National Resources Committee (Government Printing Office., 1938).
- National Resources Committee and Pacific Northwest Regional Planning Commission, 1938-1939; 1.0 folder (Box 10)
  Study of land migration problems, 1938-1939. Correspondence, memoranda, and related documents. No report. This study was known as the “land-migration-settlement-public works study.” Mr. McKinley was a consultant, especially as relating to migrant labor in Oregon, to which most of the documents refer.
- National Resources Committee. Region 10. North Pacific Planning Project, 1942-1944 (Box 10)
  Working papers, 1942-1944.
  In cooperation with the Joint Economic Committee of the United States and Canada, the National Resources Development Program in Alaska, prepared a series of economic studies of Alaska. (See files of James C. Rettie for full documentation.) Mr. McKinley was a consultant for the project. The documents include his “Notes on a conversation with Canadian officals in Victoria, re: North Pacific Planning Project, November 25 to December 3, 1942.”
- National Resources Planning Board. Region 6, 1939; 18.0 folders (Box 10)
  Administrative study of regional and state planning boards, 1939.
  Includes correspondence, reports, and interviews on the planning boards in the Pacific Northwest and Northern Great Plains states, and concerned Federal agencies. Included is Mr. McKinley’s report, in two parts: 1) “A confidential report on state and national planning in region six”; 2) “Confidential [report] to Mr. [Charles] Eliot and Mr. [P. H.] Elwood only.” (September 1, 1939).
- Northwest Forest Pest Action Committee, 1954-1965; 1.0 linear feet (Box 10)
  Minutes, 1954, memoranda, publication, and miscellaneous documents.
  The committee was formed, rather casually, in 1948 as a Spruce Budworm Action Committee, and became the Northwest Forest Pest Action Committee in April 1952. In 1959 it was styled the Pest Action Council.
  With these files are three folders of material on pesticides and their effect on the environment, 1959-1963.
  The files on the Northwest Pest Action Committee were formed by Mr. McKinley for his monograph, The Management of Land and Related Water Resources in Oregon (Washington, D. C., 1965), and are the basis for chapter 7.
- Oregon. Legislative Interim Commission on Administrative Reorganization, 1928-1930; 1.0 folder (Box 10)
  Correspondence with Hector McPherson, chairman, 1930.
  Hector McPheerson, while chairman of the Interim Commission, was also promoting an “Oregon Citizen’s League.” Advocating a “cabinet” form of government for Oregon. The correspondence is a mixture of officials Interim Committee business, and McPherson’s own promotion of the Oregon Citizen’s League. It includes replies from state officials and others in Oregon and elsewhere, to questionnaires sent out by McPherson, and a copy of col. 1 no. 1 of The Oregon Citizen, April 1928. Mr. McKinley was chairman of a special committee of the Portland City Club on the cabinet form of government.
- Oregon. Legislative Interim Committee on State Government Administration, 1949-1950; 1.0 folder (Box 10)
  Correspondence, documents, report, 1949-1950.
  The Committee, known as the “Little Hoover Committee,” was established by HJP 32, April 22, 1949. Rudie Wilhelm, Jr. was chairman, and he asked Mr. McKinley to serve on its advisory staff.
- Oregon. State Board of Forestry, 1958-1965; 1.5 linear feet (Box 11)
  Minutes, 1958-1965, reports, documents, and correspondence and interviews concerning the State Board of Forestry.
  This files was used as source material for chapter 10, “Guildism in the Oregon State Board of Forestry,” in Mr. McKinley’s monograph, The Management of Land and Related Water Resources in Oregon (Washington, D. C., 1965).
- Oregon and California Advisory Board, 1961-1969; 1.5 linear feet (Box 11-12)
  Minutes and miscellaneous papers, 1961-1969.
  On May 12, 1961 Secretary of the Interior, Stewart Udall, appointed Mr. McKinley to the O C Advisory Board. The files include minutes of the board, 1961-1969; minutes of the O C Advisory Board Committee on Allowable Cut Policies, 1966-1967, and its Report, July 25, 1967; a file on the question of sealed and oral bids for timber, 1965-1966, including a transcript of testimony before the Committee on sealed vs. oral bidding, November 23-24, 1965; a file of memoranda and correspondence concerning O C Advisory Board matters generally; a file on the Russell Getty-Charles Stoddard case, involving the proposed exchange of certain public lands in Oregon for certain land at Point Reyes, California. This file includes a manuscript by Kenneth Tollenaar, “A Revolt in the Provinces,” being a case study of the proposed transfer. There is also a file on the Association of O C Counties.
- Pacific Northwest Field Committee, 1946-1955; 2.5 linear feet (Box 12-14)
  Records, 1946-1955. Includes organizational documents, correspondence, minutes of meetings, budgetary proposals for an integrated program for the Department of the Interior in the Pacific Northwest.
  In January 1946 Secretary of the Interior Oscar L. Chapman requested proposals for Interior Department reorganization, based on the Reorganization Act of December 20, 1945 (PL 263, 79th Congress). The Office of Solicitor, Department of the Interior, on May 27, 1946, submitted a memorandum based on conferences, in which regional coordinating committees were proposed. By Interior Department Order 2205, June 4, 1946, a Coordinating Committee was established in the Department, consisting of representatives from various agencies in Interior. Interior Department Order 2221, July 3, 1946, ordered the Coordinating Committee to establish temporary field committees in major cities, and proposed regions for such committees. A Portland, Oregon Temporary Field Committee was formed in July, and in September it drafted a departmental order establishing a Pacific Northwest Coordinating Committee. On October 25, the Temporary Committee met to for the Pacific Northwest Coordinating Committee. Interior Department Order 2465, August 25, 1948, amended the purposes and organization of all coordinating committees, and designated them as Field Committees.
  Department of Agricultures Order 1257, May 1, 1950, established a Field Committee for the Columbia River Basin Area. This committee was to coordinate USDA agriculture programs in the region, and plan the department’s participation in Columbia Basin Interagency Committee activities. Minutes of this committee, and memoranda, are filed here.
  With their files are placed twelve inches of carded notes and interviews concerning integration of Interior Department programs in the Pacific Northwest and elsewhere.
- Pacific Northwest Regional Planning Commission [and others], 1935-1943; 1.5 linear feet (Box 14-15)
  Files of letters, minutes, reports and documents on national, regional, and state planning. Includes material on theory, legislation, inter-relationships, planning boards in Oregon, Washington and Idaho, and on the National Resources Committee, 1935-1943.
  This file was used by Mr. McKinley in a variety of reports, papers, and lectures, and in part for his administrative study of regional and state planning boards. (See National Planning Board. Region 6).
- President’s Committee on Administrative Management, 1936; 1.0 linear feet (Box 15-16)
  Working papers, drafts, memoranda, 1936.
  On March 20, 1936 the President created a Committee on Administrative Management to study the relation of the emergency agencies to the regular organization of the Executive Branch of the government. Mr. McKinley was on the research staff of the Committee, assigned to prepare a study on planning. The file includes administrative papers of the Committee, a progress report, June 22-August 15, 1936, and a draft report by McKinley, “A Report Concerning a Planning Organization Which Will Facilitate Presidential Management,” (October 26, 1936). There are also drafts of other Committee reports, as follows:
  A. N. Holcombe, “The Administrative principles exemplified by the War Department General Staff and their applicability to the civil departments and establishments of the Federal Government.” (August 15, 1936)
  Robert E. Cushman, “The problem of the independent regulatory commissions.” (October 15, 1936).
  Patterson H. French, “Government corporations.” (October 15, 1936)
  Mary C. Trackett, “Case studies of interdepartmental committees.” (September, 1936)
  Mary C. Trackett, “Interdepartmental committees.” (September, 1936)
  Schuyler C. Wallace, “Administrative reorganization in relation to administrative management,” (September 25, 1936).
  Most of these reports were published in the Committee’s Report (U. S. Government Printing Offices, 1937).
  With these files are six inches of carded notes and interviews on government planning, assembled by Mr. McKinley for his report.
- President’s Water Resources Policy Commission, 1950; 0.5 linear feet (Box 16)
  Working papers, 1950. Includes administrative correspondence, documents and draft reports concerning planning, the benefit-cost problem, cost allocation, reimbursement, and the 160-acre limitation. 1950.
  By Executive Order 10095, January 3, 1950, the President established the Water Resources Policy Commission in the Executive Office of the President. The Commission was to study and make recommendations concerning Federal responsibility for and participation in development, utilization and conservation of water resources. The emphasis on most problems was economic and social. Mr. McKinley was consultant to the Committee.